<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<elements>
	<info>
		<name>Wizard: Spycraft</name>
		<update version="0.1.0">
			<file name="subclass-wizarwd-spycraft.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/MeriadarGoblin/elements-portent-press/main/major-arcana/oranas-expanded-spellbook/subclass-wizard-spycraft.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>

	<element name="Spycraft" type="Archetype Feature" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_ARCHETYPE_WIZARD_SPYCRAFT">
		<supports>Arcane Tradition</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Wizards of this tradition focus on magic that allows them to achieve very specific goals; primarily reconnaissance, theft, and sabotage. They use powerful illusions to hide their machinations, as well as Divination magic that lets them gather information unseen and unheard. They make excellent spymasters, working either for themselves or as court wizards for a higher authority that needs their services. Some wizards even use their talents against others of their kind, weaving webs of intrigue that afford them opportunities to steal others' arcane discoveries.</p>
			<div element="ID_PP_OES_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_SPYCRAFT_SAVANT" />
			<div element="ID_PP_OES_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_SPYCRAFT_ARCANE_ESPIONAGE" />
			<div element="ID_PP_OES_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_SPYCRAFT_IDENTITY_SWAP" />
			<div element="ID_PP_OES_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_SPYCRAFT_CROSS_EXAMINATION" />
			<div element="ID_PP_OES_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_SPYCRAFT_SILENT_CASTING" />
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_PP_OES_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_SPYCRAFT_SAVANT" level="2" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_PP_OES_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_SPYCRAFT_ARCANE_ESPIONAGE" level="2" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_PP_OES_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_SPYCRAFT_IDENTITY_SWAP" level="6" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_PP_OES_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_SPYCRAFT_CROSS_EXAMINATION" level="10" />
			<grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_PP_OES_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_SPYCRAFT_SILENT_CASTING" level="14" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Spycraft Savant" type="Archetype Feature" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_SPYCRAFT_SAVANT">
		<description>
			<p>The time and gold you must spend to copy a spell with the spycraft tag into your spellbook is halved.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>The time and gold you must spend to copy a spell with the spycraft tag into your spellbook is halved.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Arcane Espionage" type="Archetype Feature" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_SPYCRAFT_ARCANE_ESPIONAGE">
		<description>
			<p>Your magic improves your subtlety. You gain proficiency in the Deception and Stealth skills.</p>
			<p class="indent">Additionally, you can weave defenses and further subtlety into your deception. While you are invisible, your true form is concealed by Illusion or Transmutation magic, or you are concentrating on a spell with the spycraft spell tag, your proficiency bonus is doubled for any ability check you make that uses Deception or Stealth, and you gain a bonus to your AC equal to your Intelligence modifier (minimum of +1).</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>While you are invisible, your true form is concealed by Illusion or Transmutation magic, or you are concentrating on a spell with the spycraft spell tag, your proficiency bonus is doubled for any ability check you make that uses Deception or Stealth, and you gain a +{{arcane espionage:ac}} to AC.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="arcane espionage:ac" value="1" bonus="base" />
			<stat name="arcane espionage:ac" value="intelligence:modifier" bonus="base" />
			<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_SKILL_DECEPTION" />
			<grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_SKILL_STEALTH" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Identity Swap" type="Archetype Feature" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_SPYCRAFT_IDENTITY_SWAP">
		<description>
			<p>You add the characterize spell to your spellbook if it is not there already, it counts as a wizard spell for you, and it gains the spycraft tag. You can cast characterize without expending a spell slot. When you do so, you can target only yourself and another willing creature. While you and the target are affected by this casting of characterize, the disguise does not appear magical to divination spells.</p>
			<p class="indent">Once you cast characterize in this way, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest, though you can still cast it normally using an available spell slot.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet usage="Short/Long Rest">
			<description>You can cast characterize without expending a spell slot. When you do so, you can target only yourself and another willing creature. While you and the target are affected by this casting of characterize, the disguise does not appear magical to divination spells. Once you cast characterize in this way, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest, though you can still cast it normally using an available spell slot.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<grant type="Spell" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_CHARACTERIZE" spellcasting="Wizard" prepared="true" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Cross Examination" type="Archetype Feature" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_SPYCRAFT_CROSS_EXAMINATION">
		<description>
			<p>Your spells loosen the tongues of your enemies. When you cast a wizard spell of 1st-level or higher that requires a saving throw, choose one of the creatures that failed its save; it can't speak a deliberate lie for the spell's duration and knows this fact. If the spell has the spycraft tag, it is instead unaware of its compelled truth.</p>
			<p class="indent">Additionally, you always know when you are targeted by or are being perceived by a Divination spell. When a creature casts a Divination spell that would perceive, reveal, or otherwise affect you, you can use your reaction to perceive the creature for the duration of the spell, as if by the scrying spell or see invisibility spell; doing so does not blind or deafen you to your own senses. If you succeed on the saving throw against the spell, you can also provide the creature false information about what it would perceive as part of the same reaction, which it believes.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>When you cast a wizard spell of 1st-level or higher that requires a saving throw, choose one of the creatures that failed its save; it can't speak a deliberate lie for the spell's duration and knows this fact. If the spell has the spycraft tag, it is instead unaware of its compelled truth. Additionally, you always know when you are targeted by or are being perceived by a Divination spell. When a creature casts a Divination spell that would perceive, reveal, or otherwise affect you, you can use your reaction to perceive the creature for the duration of the spell, as if by the scrying spell or see invisibility spell; doing so does not blind or deafen you to your own senses. If you succeed on the saving throw against the spell, you can also provide the creature false information about what it would perceive as part of the same reaction, which it believes.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Silent Casting" type="Archetype Feature" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_ARCHETYPE_FEATURE_SPYCRAFT_SILENT_CASTING">
		<description>
			<p>You can cast spells without drawing attention to yourself. When you cast a spell with the spycraft tag, you can cast it without verbal or somatic components.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You can cast spells without drawing attention to yourself. When you cast a spell with the spycraft tag, you can cast it without verbal or somatic components.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<!-- Spycraft Spells -->
	<element name="Mage Hand" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_MAGE_HAND">
		<supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Artificer</supports>
		<description>
			<p>A spectral, floating hand appears at a point you choose within range. The hand lasts for the duration or until you dismiss it as an action. The hand vanishes if it is ever more than 30 feet away from you or if you cast this spell again.</p>
			<p class="indent">You can use your action to control the hand. You can use the hand to manipulate an object, open an unlocked door or container, stow or retrieve an item from an open container, or pour the contents out of a vial. You can move the hand up to 30 feet each time you use it.</p>
			<p class="indent">The hand can’t attack, activate magic items, or carry more than 10 pounds.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">0</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Conjuration</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">1 minute</set>
			<set name="range">30 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent" />
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Message" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_MESSAGE">
		<supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Wizard, Artificer</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You point your finger toward a creature within range and whisper a message. The target (and only the target) hears the message and can reply in a whisper that only you can hear.</p>
			<p class="indent">You can cast this spell through solid objects if you are familiar with the target and know it is beyond the barrier. Magical silence, 1 foot of stone, 1 inch of common metal, a thin sheet of lead, or 3 feet of wood blocks the spell. The spell doesn’t have to follow a straight line and can travel freely around corners or through openings.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">0</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Transmutation</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">1 round</set>
			<set name="range">120 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a short piece of copper wire</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>

	<!-- 1ST LEVEL -->
	<element name="Alarm" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_ALARM">
		<supports>Ranger, Wizard, Artificer</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You set an alarm against unwanted intrusion. Choose a door, a window, or an area within range that is no larger than a 20-foot cube. Until the spell ends, an alarm alerts you whenever a tiny or larger creature touches or enters the warded area. When you cast the spell, you can designate creatures that won’t set off the alarm. You also choose whether the alarm is mental or audible.</p>
			<p class="indent">A mental alarm alerts you with a ping in your mind if you are within 1 mile of the warded area. This ping awakens you if you are sleeping.</p>
			<p class="indent">An audible alarm produces the sound of a hand bell for 10 seconds within 60 feet.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">1</set>
			<set name="school"  addition="Spycraft">Abjuration</set>
			<set name="time">1 minute</set>
			<set name="duration">8 hours</set>
			<set name="range">30 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a tiny bell and a piece of fine silver wire</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">true</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Charm Person" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_CHARM_PERSON">
		<supports>Bard, Druid, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Spell Saving Throw</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You attempt to charm a humanoid you can see within range. It must make a Wisdom saving throw, and does so with advantage if you or your companions are fighting it. If it fails the saving throw, it is charmed by you until the spell ends or until you or your companions do anything harmful to it. The charmed creature regards you as a friendly acquaintance. When the spell ends, the creature knows it was charmed by you.</p>
			<p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, you can target one additional creature for each slot level above 1st. The creatures must be within 30 feet of each other when you target them.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords">charm</set>
			<set name="level">1</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Enchantment</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">1 hour</set>
			<set name="range">30 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent" />
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Detect Magic" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_DETECT_MAGIC">
		<supports>Bard, Cleric, Druid, Paladin, Ranger, Sorcerer, Wizard, Artificer</supports>
		<description>
			<p>For the duration, you sense the presence of magic within 30 feet of you. If you sense magic in this way, you can use your action to see a faint aura around any visible creature or object in the area that bears magic, and you learn its school of magic, if any.</p>
			<p class="indent">The spell can penetrate most barriers, but is blocked by 1 foot of stone, 1 inch of common metal, a thin sheet of lead, or 3 feet of wood or dirt.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">1</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Divination</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
			<set name="range">Self</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent" />
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">true</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Disguise Self" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_DISGUISE_SELF">
		<supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Wizard, Artificer</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You make yourself—including your clothing, armor, weapons, and other belongings on your person—look different until the spell ends or until you use your action to dismiss it. You can seem 1 foot shorter or taller and can appear thin, fat, or in between. You can’t change your body type, so you must adopt a form that has the same basic arrangement of limbs. Otherwise, the extent of the illusion is up to you.</p>
			<p class="indent">The changes wrought by this spell fail to hold up to physical inspection. For example, if you use this spell to add a hat to your outfit, objects pass through the hat, and anyone who touches it would feel nothing or would feel your head and hair. If you use this spell to appear thinner than you are, the hand of someone who reaches out to touch you would bump into you while it was seemingly still in midair.</p>
			<p class="indent">To discern that you are disguised, a creature can use its action to inspect your appearance and must succeed on an Intelligence (Investigation) check against your spell save DC.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">1</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Illusion</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">1 hour</set>
			<set name="range">Self</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent" />
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Fog Cloud" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_FOG_CLOUD">
		<supports>Druid, Ranger, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You create a 20-foot-radius sphere of fog centered on a point within range. The sphere spreads around corners, and its area is heavily obscured, It lasts for the duration or until a wind of moderate or greater speed (at least 10 miles per hour) disperses it.</p>
			<p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the radius of the fog increases by 20 feet for each slot level above 1st.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">1</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Conjuration</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
			<set name="range">120 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent" />
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Illusory Script" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_ILLUSORY_SCRIPT">
		<supports>Bard, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You write on parchment, paper, or some other suitable writing material and imbue it with a potent illusion that lasts for the duration.</p>
			<p class="indent">To you and any creatures you designate when you cast the spell, the writing appears normal, written in your hand, and conveys whatever meaning you intended when you wrote the text. To all others, the writing appears as if it were written in an unknown or magical script that is unintelligible. Alternatively, you can cause the writing to appear to be an entirely different message, written in a different hand and language, though the language must be one you know.</p>
			<p class="indent">Should the spell be dispelled, the original script and the illusion both disappear.</p>
			<p class="indent">A creature with truesight can read the hidden message.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">1</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Illusion</set>
			<set name="time">1 minute</set>
			<set name="duration">10 days</set>
			<set name="range">Touch</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a lead-based ink worth at least 10 gp, which the spell consumes</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">true</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Sleep" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_SLEEP">
		<supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>This spell sends creatures into a magical slumber. Roll 5d8, the total is how many hit points of creatures this spell can affect. Creatures within 20 feet of a point you choose within range are affected in ascending order of their current hit points (ignoring unconscious creatures).</p>
			<p class="indent">Starting with the creature that has the lowest current hit points, each creature affected by this spell falls unconscious until the spell ends, the sleeper takes damage, or someone uses an action to shake or slap the sleeper awake. Subtract each creature’s hit points from the total before moving on to the creature with the next lowest hit points. A creature’s hit points must be equal to or less than the remaining total for that creature to be affected.</p>
			<p class="indent">Undead and creatures immune to being charmed aren’t affected by this spell.</p>
			<p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, roll an additional 2d8 for each slot level above 1st.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">1</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Enchantment</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">1 minute</set>
			<set name="range">90 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a pinch of fine sand, rose petals, or a cricket</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>

	<!-- 2ND LEVEL -->
	<element name="Alter Self" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_ALTER_SELF">
		<supports>Sorcerer, Wizard, Artificer</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You assume a different form. When you cast the spell, choose one of the following options, the effects of which last for the duration of the spell. While the spell lasts, you can end one option as an action to gain the benefits of a different one.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Aquatic Adaptation.</em></strong> You adapt your body to an aquatic environment, sprouting gills, and growing webbing between your fingers. You can breathe underwater and gain a swimming speed equal to your walking speed.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Change Appearance.</em></strong> You transform your appearance. You decide what you look like, including your height, weight, facial features, sound of your voice, hair length, coloration, and distinguishing characteristics, if any. You can make yourself appear as a member of another race, though none of your statistics change. You also don’t appear as a creature of a different size than you, and your basic shape stays the same; if you’re bipedal, you can’t use this spell to become quadrupedal, for instance. At any time for the duration of the spell, you can use your action to change your appearance in this way again.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Natural Weapons.</em></strong> You grow claws, fangs, spines, horns, or a different natural weapon of your choice. Your unarmed strikes deal 1d6 bludgeoning, piercing, or slashing damage, as appropriate to the natural weapon you chose, and you are proficient with your unarmed strikes. Finally, the natural weapon is magic and you have a +1 bonus to the attack and damage rolls you make using it.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">2</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Transmutation</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
			<set name="range">Self</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent" />
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Arcane Lock" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_ARCANE_LOCK">
		<supports>Wizard, Artificer</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You touch a closed door, window, gate, chest, or other entryway, and it becomes locked for the duration. You and the creatures you designate when you cast this spell can open the object normally. You can also set a password that, when spoken within 5 feet of the object, suppresses this spell for 1 minute. Otherwise, it is impassable until it is broken or the spell is dispelled or suppressed. Casting knock on the object suppresses arcane lock for 10 minutes.</p>
			<p class="indent">While affected by this spell, the object is more difficult to break or force open; the DC to break it or pick any locks on it increases by 10.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">2</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Abjuration</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Until dispelled</set>
			<set name="range">Touch</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">gold dust worth at least 25 gp, which the spell consumes</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Nystul’s Magic Aura" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_NYSTULS_MAGIC_AURA">
		<supports>Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You place an illusion on a creature or an object you touch so that divination spells reveal false information about it. The target can be a willing creature or an object that isn’t being carried or worn by another creature.</p>
			<p class="indent">When you cast the spell, choose one or both of the following effects. The effect lasts for the duration. If you cast this spell on the same creature or object every day for 30 days, placing the same effect on it each time, the illusion lasts until it is dispelled.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><i>False Aura. </i></strong>You change the way the target appears to spells and magical effects, such as detect magic, that detect magical auras. You can make a nonmagical object appear magical, a magical object appear nonmagical, or change the object’s magical aura so that it appears to belong to a specific school of magic that you choose. When you use this effect on an object, you can make the false magic apparent to any creature that handles the item.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><i>Mask. </i></strong>You change the way the target appears to spells and magical effects that detect creature types, such as a paladin’s Divine Sense or the trigger of a symbol spell. You choose a creature type and other spells and magical effects treat the target as if it were a creature of that type or of that alignment.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">2</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Illusion</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">24 hours</set>
			<set name="range">Touch</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a small square of silk</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Detect Thoughts" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_DETECT_THOUGHTS">
		<supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Wizard, Spell Saving Throw</supports>
		<description>
			<p>For the duration, you can read the thoughts of certain creatures. When you cast the spell and as your action on each turn until the spell ends, you can focus your mind on any one creature that you can see within 30 feet of you. If the creature you choose has an Intelligence of 3 or lower or doesn’t speak any language, the creature is unaffected.</p>
			<p class="indent">You initially learn the surface thoughts of the creature—what is most on its mind in that moment. As an action, you can either shift your attention to another creature’s thoughts or attempt to probe deeper into the same creature’s mind. If you probe deeper, the target must make a Wisdom saving throw. If it fails, you gain insight into its reasoning (if any), its emotional state, and something that looms large in its mind (such as something it worries over, loves, or hates). If it succeeds, the spell ends. Either way, the target knows that you are probing into its mind, and unless you shift your attention to another creature’s thoughts, the creature can use its action on its turn to make an Intelligence check contested by your Intelligence check; if it succeeds, the spell ends.</p>
			<p class="indent">Questions verbally directed at the target creature naturally shape the course of its thoughts, so this spell is particularly effective as part of an interrogation.</p>
			<p class="indent">You can also use this spell to detect the presence of thinking creatures you can’t see. When you cast the spell or as your action during the duration, you can search for thoughts within 30 feet of you. The spell can penetrate barriers, but 2 feet of rock, 2 inches of any metal other than lead, or a thin sheet of lead blocks you. You can’t detect a creature with an Intelligence of 3 or lower or one that doesn’t speak any language.</p>
			<p class="indent">Once you detect the presence of a creature in this way, you can read its thoughts for the rest of the duration as described above, even if you can’t see it, but it must still be within range.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">2</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Divination</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
			<set name="range">Self</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a copper piece</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Invisibility" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_INVISIBILITY">
		<supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Artificer</supports>
		<description>
			<p>A creature you touch becomes invisible until the spell ends. Anything the target is wearing or carrying is invisible as long as it is on the target’s person. The spell ends for a target that attacks or casts a spell.</p>
			<p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, you can target one additional creature for each slot level above 2nd.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">2</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Illusion</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
			<set name="range">Touch</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">an eyelash encased in gum arabic</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Knock" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_KNOCK">
		<supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Choose an object that you can see within range. The object can be a door, a box, a chest, a set of manacles, a padlock, or another object that contains a mundane or magical means that prevents access.</p>
			<p class="indent">A target that is held shut by a mundane lock or that is stuck or barred becomes unlocked, unstuck, or unbarred. If the object has multiple locks, only one of them is unlocked.</p>
			<p class="indent">If you choose a target that is held shut with arcane lock, that spell is suppressed for 10 minutes, during which time the target can be opened and shut normally.</p>
			<p class="indent">When you cast the spell, a loud knock, audible from as far away as 300 feet, emanates from the target object.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">2</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Transmutation</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
			<set name="range">60 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent" />
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Locate Object" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_LOCATE_OBJECT">
		<supports>Bard, Cleric, Druid, Paladin, Ranger, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Describe or name an object that is familiar to you. You sense the direction to the object’s location, as long as that object is within 1,000 feet of you. If the object is in motion, you know the direction of its movement.</p>
			<p class="indent">The spell can locate a specific object known to you, as long as you have seen it up close - within 30 feet - at least once. Alternatively, the spell can locate the nearest object of a particular kind, such as a certain kind of apparel, jewelry, furniture, tool, or weapon.</p>
			<p class="indent">This spell can’t locate an object if any thickness of lead, even a thin sheet, blocks a direct path between you and the object.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">2</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Divination</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
			<set name="range">Self</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a forked twig</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Suggestion" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_SUGGESTION">
		<supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Spell Saving Throw</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You suggest a course of activity (limited to a sentence or two) and magically influence a creature you can see within range that can hear and understand you. Creatures that can’t be charmed are immune to this effect. The suggestion must be worded in such a manner as to make the course of action sound reasonable. Asking the creature to stab itself, throw itself onto a spear, immolate itself, or do some other obviously harmful act ends the spell.</p>
			<p class="indent">The target must make a Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, it purses the course of action you described to the best of its ability. The suggested course of action can continue for the entire duration. If the suggested activity can be completed in a shorter time, the spell ends when the subject finishes what it was asked to do.</p>
			<p class="indent">You can also specify conditions that will trigger a special activity during the duration. For example, you might suggest that a knight give her warhorse to the first beggar she meets.</p>
			<p class="indent">If the condition isn’t met before the spell expires, the activity isn’t preformed. If you or any of your companions damage the target, the spell ends.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">2</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Enchantment</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 8 hours</set>
			<set name="range">30 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a snake’s tongue and either a bit of honeycomb or a drop of sweet oil</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>

	<!-- 3RD LEVEL -->
	<element name="Clairvoyance" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_CLAIRVOYANCE">
		<supports>Bard, Cleric, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You create an invisible sensor within range in a location familiar to you (a place you have visited or seen before) or in an obvious location that is unfamiliar to you (such as behind a door, around a corner, or in a grove of trees). The sensor remains in place for the duration, and it can’t be attacked or otherwise interacted with</p>
			<p class="indent">When you cast the spell, you choose seeing or hearing. You can use the chosen sense through the sensor as if you were in its space. As your action, you can switch between seeing and hearing.</p>
			<p class="indent">A creature that can see the sensor (such as a creature benefitting from see invisibility or truesight) sees a luminous, intangible orb about the size of your fist.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">3</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Divination</set>
			<set name="time">10 minutes</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
			<set name="range">1 mile</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a focus worth at least 100 gp, either a jeweled horn for hearing or a glass eye for scrying</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Nondetection" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_NONDETECTION">
		<supports>Bard, Ranger, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>For the duration, you hide a target that you touch from divination magic. The target can be a willing creature or a place or an object no larger than 10 feet in any dimension. The target can’t be targeted by any divination magic or perceived through magical scrying sensors.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">3</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Abjuration</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">8 hours</set>
			<set name="range">Touch</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a pinch of diamond dust worth 25 gp sprinkled over the target, which the spell consumes</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Sending" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_SENDING">
		<supports>Bard, Cleric, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You send a short message of twenty-five words or less to a creature with you are familiar. The creature hears the message in its mind, recognizes you as the sender if it knows you, and can answer in a like manner immediately. The spell enables creatures with Intelligence scores of at least 1 to understand the meaning of your message.</p>
			<p class="indent">You can send the message across any distance and even to other planes of existence, but if the target is on a different plane than you, there is a 5 percent chance that the message doesn’t arrive.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">3</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Evocation</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">1 round</set>
			<set name="range">Unlimited</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">A short piece of fine copper wire</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Tongues" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_TONGUES">
		<supports>Bard, Cleric, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>This spell grants the creature you touch the ability to understand any spoken language it hears. Moreover, when the target speaks, any creature that knows at least one language and can hear the target understands what it says.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">3</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Divination</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">1 hour</set>
			<set name="range">Touch</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a small clay model of a ziggurat</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>

	<!-- 4TH LEVEL -->
	<element name="Arcane Eye" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_ARCANE_EYE">
		<supports>Wizard, Artificer</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You create an invisible, magical eye within range that hovers in the air for the duration.</p>
			<p class="indent">You mentally receive visual information from the eye, which has normal vision and darkvision out to 30 feet. The eye can look in every direction.</p>
			<p class="indent">As an action, you can move the eye up to 30 feet in any direction. There is no limit to how far away from you the eye can move, but it can’t enter another plane of existence. A solid barrier blocks the eye’s movement, but the eye can pass through an opening as small as 1 inch in diameter.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">4</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Divination</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
			<set name="range">30 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a bit of bat fur</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Confusion" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_CONFUSION">
		<supports>Bard, Druid, Sorcerer, Wizard, Spell Saving Throw</supports>
		<description>
			<p>This spell assaults and twists creatures’ minds, spawning delusions and provoking uncontrolled actions. Each creature in a 10-foot-radius sphere centered on a point you choose within range must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw when you cast this spell or be affected by it.</p>
			<p class="indent">An affected target can’t take reactions and must roll a d10 at the start of each of its turns to determine its behavior for that turn.</p>
			<table>
				<tr><td>d10</td><td class="left">Behavior</td></tr>
				<tr><td>1</td><td class="left">The creature uses all its movement to move in a random direction. To determine the direction, roll a d8 and assign a direction to each die face. The creature doesn’t take an action this turn.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>2-6</td><td class="left">The creature doesn’t move or take actions this turn.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>7-8</td><td class="left">The creature uses its action to make a melee attack against a randomly determined creature within its reach. If there is no creature within its reach, the creature does nothing this turn.</td></tr>
				<tr><td>9-10</td><td class="left">The creature can act and move normally.</td></tr>
			</table>
			<p class="indent">At the end of its turns, an affected target can make a Wisdom saving throw. It it succeeds, this effect ends for that target.</p>
			<p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, the radius of the sphere increases by 5 feet for each slot above 4th.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">4</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Enchantment</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
			<set name="range">90 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">three nut shells</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Dimension Door" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_DIMENSION_DOOR">
		<supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You teleport yourself from your current location to any other spot within range. You arrive at exactly the spot desired. It can be a place you can see, one you can visualize, or one you can describe by stating distance and direction, such as “200 feet straight downward” or “upward to the northwest at a 45-degree angle, 300 feet.”</p>
			<p class="indent">You can bring along objects as long as their weight doesn’t exceed what you can carry. You can also bring one willing creature of your size or smaller who is carrying gear up to its carrying capacity. The creature must be within 5 feet of you when you cast this spell.</p>
			<p class="indent">If you would arrive in a place already occupied by an object or a creature, you and any creature traveling with you each take 4d6 force damage, and the spell fails to teleport you.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords">teleport</set>
			<set name="level">4</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Conjuration</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
			<set name="range">500 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent" />
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Greater Invisibility" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_GREATER_INVISIBILITY">
		<supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You or a creature you touch becomes invisible until the spell ends. Anything the target is wearing or carrying is invisible as long as it is on the target’s person.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">4</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Illusion</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
			<set name="range">Touch</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent" />
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Locate Creature" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_LOCATE_CREATURE">
		<supports>Bard, Cleric, Druid, Paladin, Ranger, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Describe or name a creature that is familiar to you. You sense the direction to the creature’s location, as long as that creature is within 1,000 feet of you. If the creature is moving, you know the direction of its movement.</p>
			<p class="indent">The spell can locate a specific creature known to you, or the nearest creature of a specific kind (such as a human or a unicorn), so long as you have seen such a creature up close - within 30 feet - at least once. If the creature you described or named is in a different form, such as being under the effects of a polymorph spell, this spell doesn’t locate the creature.</p>
			<p class="indent">This spell can’t locate a creature if running water at least 10 feet wide blocks a direct path between you and the creature.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">4</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Divination</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
			<set name="range">Self</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a bit of fur from a bloodhound</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Leomund’s Secret Chest" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_LEOMUNDS_SECRET_CHEST">
		<supports>Wizard, Artificer</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You hide a chest, and all its contents, on the Ethereal Plane. You must touch the chest and the miniature replica that serves as a material component for the spell. The chest can contain up to 12 cubic feet of nonliving material (3 feet by 2 feet by 2 feet).</p>
			<p class="indent">While the chest remains on the Ethereal Plane, you can use an action and touch the replica to recall the chest. It appears in an unoccupied space on the ground within 5 feet of you. You can send the chest back to the Ethereal Plane by using an action and touching both the chest and the replica.</p>
			<p class="indent">After 60 days, there is a cumulative 5 percent chance per day that the spell’s effect ends. This effect ends if you cast this spell again, if the smaller replica chest is destroyed, or if you choose to end the spell as an action. If the spell ends and the larger chest is on the Ethereal Plane, it is irretrievably lost.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">4</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Conjuration</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
			<set name="range">Touch</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">an exquisite chest, 3 feet by 2 feet by 2 feet, constructed from rare materials worth at least 5,000 gp, and a Tiny replica made from the same materials worth at least 50 gp</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	
	<!-- 5TH LEVEL -->
	<element name="Dominate Person" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_DOMINATE_PERSON">
		<supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Wizard, Spell Saving Throw</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You attempt to beguile a humanoid that you can see within range. It must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or be charmed by you for the duration. If you or creatures that are friendly to you are fighting it, it has advantage on the saving throw.</p>
			<p class="indent">While the target is charmed, you have a telepathic link with it as long as the two of you are on the same plane of existence. You can use this telepathic link to issue commands to the creature while you are conscious (no action required), which it does its best to obey. You can specify a simple and general course of action, such as “Attack that creature,” “Run over there,” or “Fetch that object.” If the creature completes the order and doesn’t receive further direction from you, it defends and preserves itself to the best of its ability.</p>
			<p class="indent">You can use your action to take total and precise control of the target. Until the end of your next turn, the creature takes only the actions you choose, and doesn’t do anything that you don’t allow it to do. During this time you can also cause the creature to use a reaction, but this requires you to use your own reaction as well.</p>
			<p class="indent">Each time the target takes damage, it makes a new Wisdom saving throw against the spell. If the saving throw succeeds, the spell ends.</p>
			<p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a 6th-level spell slot, the duration is concentration, up to 10 minutes. When you use a 7th-level spell slot, the duration is concentration, up to 1 hour. When you use a spell slot of 8th level or higher, the duration is concentration, up to 8 hours.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">5</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Enchantment</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
			<set name="range">60 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent" />
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Legend Lore" type="Spell" source="book" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_LEGEND_LORE">
		<supports>Bard, Cleric, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Name or describe a person, place, or object. The spell brings to your mind a brief summary of the significant lore about the thing you named. The lore might consist of current tales, forgotten stories, or even secret lore that has never been widely known. If the thing you named isn’t of legendary importance, you gain no information. The more information you already have about the thing, the more precise and detailed the information you receive is.</p>
			<p class="indent">The information you learn is accurate but might be couched in figurative language. For example, if you have a mysterious magic axe on hand, the spell might yield this information: Woe to the evildoer whose hand touches the axe, for even the haft slices the hand of the evil ones. Only a true Child of Stone, lover and beloved of Moradin, may awaken the true powers of the axe, and only with the sacred word Rudnogg on the lips.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">5</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Divination</set>
			<set name="time">10 minutes</set>
			<set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
			<set name="range">Self</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">incense worth at least 250 gp, which the spell consumes, and four ivory strips worth at least 50 gp each</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Mislead" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_MISLEAD">
		<supports>Bard, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You become invisible at the same time that an illusory double of you appears where you are standing. The double lasts for the duration, but the invisibility ends if you attack or cast a spell.</p>
			<p class="indent">You can use your action to move your illusory double up to twice your speed and make it gesture, speak, and behave in whatever way you choose.</p>
			<p class="indent">You can see through its eyes and hear through its ears as if you were located where it is. On each of your turns as a bonus action, you can switch from using its senses to using your own, or back again. While you are using its senses, you are blinded and deafened in regard to your own surroundings.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">5</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Illusion</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
			<set name="range">Self</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">false</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent" />
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Modify Memory" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_MODIFY_MEMORY">
		<supports>Bard, Wizard, Spell Saving Throw</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You attempt to reshape another creature’s memories. One creature that you can see must make a Wisdom saving throw. If you are fighting the creature, it has advantage on the saving throw. On a failed save, the target becomes charmed by you for the duration. The charmed target is incapacitated and unaware of its surroundings, though it can still hear you. If it takes any damage or is targeted by another spell, this spell ends, and none of the target’s memories are modified.</p>
			<p class="indent">While this charm lasts, you can affect the target’s memory of an event that it experienced within the last 24 hours and that lasted no more than 10 minutes. You can permanently eliminate all memory of the event, allow the target to recall the event with perfect clarity and exacting detail, change its memory of the details of the event, or create a memory of some other event.</p>
			<p class="indent">You must speak to the target to describe how its memories are affected, and it must be able to understand your language for the modified memories to take root. Its mind fills in any gaps in the details of your description. If the spell ends before you have finished describing the modified memories, the creature’s memory isn’t altered. Otherwise, the modified memories take hold when the spell ends.</p>
			<p class="indent">A modified memory doesn’t necessarily affect how a creature behaves, particularly if the memory contradicts the creature’s natural inclinations, alignment, or beliefs. An illogical modified memory, such as implanting a memory of how much the creature enjoyed dousing itself in acid, is dismissed, perhaps as a bad dream. The DM might deem a modified memory too nonsensical to affect a creature in a significant manner.</p>
			<p class="indent">A <i>remove curse</i> or <i>greater restoration</i> spell cast on the target restores the creature’s true memory.</p>
			<p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> If you cast this spell using a spell slot of 6th level or higher, you can alter the target’s memories of an event that took place up to 7 days ago (6th level), 30 days ago (7th level), 1 year ago (8th level), or any time in the creature’s past (9th level).</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">5</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Enchantment</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 minute</set>
			<set name="range">30 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent" />
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Passwall" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_PASSWALL">
		<supports>Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>A passage appears at a point of your choice that you can see on a wooden, plaster, or stone surface (such as a wall, a ceiling, or a floor) within range, and lasts for the duration. You choose the opening's dimensions: up to 5 feet wide, 8 feet tall, and 20 feet deep. The passage creates no instability in a structure surrounding it.</p>
			<p class="indent">When the opening disappears, any creatures or objects still in the passage created by the spell are safely ejected to an unoccupied space nearest to the surface on which you cast the spell.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">5</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Transmutation</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">1 hour</set>
			<set name="range">30 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a pinch of sesame seeds</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Scrying" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_SCRYING">
		<supports>Bard, Cleric, Druid, Warlock, Wizard, Spell Saving Throw</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You can see and hear a particular creature you choose that is on the same plane of existence as you. The target must make a Wisdom saving throw, which is modified by how well you know the target and the sort of physical connection you have to it. If a target knows you're casting this spell, it can fail the saving throw voluntarily if it wants to be observed.</p>
			<table>
				<thead>
					<tr><td class="left">Knowledge</td><td>Save Modifier</td></tr>
				</thead>
				<tr><td class="left">Secondhand (you have heard of the target)</td><td>+5</td></tr>
				<tr><td class="left">Firsthand (you have met the target)</td><td>0</td></tr>
				<tr><td class="left">Familiar (you know the target well)</td><td>-5</td></tr>
			</table>
			<table>
				<thead>
					<tr><td class="left">Connection</td><td>Save Modifier</td></tr>
				</thead>
				<tr><td class="left">Likeness or picture</td><td>-2</td></tr>
				<tr><td class="left">Possession or garment</td><td>-4</td></tr>
				<tr><td class="left">Body part, lock of hair, bit of nail, or the like</td><td>-10</td></tr>
			</table>
			<p class="indent">On a successful save, the target isn't affected, and you can't use this spell against it again for 24 hours.</p>
			<p class="indent">On a failed save, the spell creates an invisible sensor within 10 feet of the target. You can see and hear through the sensor as if you were there. The sensor moves with the target, remaining within 10 feet of it for the duration. A creature that can see invisible objects sees the sensor as a luminous orb about the size of your fist.</p>
			<p class="indent">Instead of targeting a creature, you can choose a location you have seen before as the target of this spell. When you do, the sensor appears at that location and doesn't move.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">5</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Divination</set>
			<set name="time">10 minutes</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 10 minutes</set>
			<set name="range">Self</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a focus worth at least 1,000 gp, such as a crystal ball, a silver mirror, or a font filled with holy water</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Seeming" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_SEEMING">
		<supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Wizard, Spell Saving Throw</supports>
		<description>
			<p>This spell allows you to change the appearance of any number of creatures that you can see within range. You give each target you choose a new, illusory appearance. An unwilling target can make a Charisma saving throw, and if it succeeds, it is unaffected by this spell.</p>
			<p class="indent">The spell disguises physical appearances as well as clothing, armor, weapons, and equipment. You can make each creature seem 1 foot shorter or taller and appear thin, fat, or in between. You can’t change a target’s body type, so you must choose a form that has the same basic arrangement of limbs. Otherwise, the extent of the illusion is up to you. The spell lasts for the duration, unless you use your action to dismiss it sooner.</p>
			<p class="indent">The changes wrought by this spell fail to hold up to physical inspections. For example, if you use this spell to add a hat to a creature’s outfit objects pass through the hat, and anyone who touches it would feel nothing or would feel the creature’s head and hair. If you use this spell to appear thinner then you are, the hand of someone who reaches out to touch you would bump into you while it was seemingly still in midair.</p>
			<p class="indent">A creature can use its action to inspect a target and make an Intelligence (Investigation) check against your spell save DC. If it succeeds, it becomes aware that the target is disguised.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">5</set>
			<set name="school " addition="Spycraft">Illusion</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">8 hours</set>
			<set name="range">30 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent" />
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Rary’s Telepathic Bond" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_RARYS_TELEPATHIC_BOND">
		<supports>Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You forge a telepathic link among up to eight willing creatures of your choice within range, psychically linking each creature to all the others for the duration. Creatures with Intelligence scores of 2 or less aren’t affected by this spell.</p>
			<p class="indent">Until the spell ends, the targets can communicated telepathically through the bond whether or not they have a common language. The communication is possible over any distance, though it can’t extend to other planes of existence.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">5</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Divination</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">1 hour</set>
			<set name="range">30 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">pieces of eggshell from two different kinds of creatures</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">true</set>
		</setters>
	</element>

	<!-- 6TH LEVEL -->
	<element name="Contingency" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_CONTINGENCY">
		<supports>Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Choose a spell of 5th level or lower that you can cast, that has a casting time of 1 action, and that can target you. You cast that spell—called the contingent spell—as part of casting contingency, expending spell slots for both, but the contingent spell doesn’t come into effect. Instead, it takes effect when a certain circumstance occurs. You describe that circumstance when you cast the two spells. For example, a contingency cast with water breathing might stipulate that water breathing comes into effect when you are engulfed in water or a similar liquid.</p>
			<p class="indent">The contingent spell takes effect immediately after the circumstance is met for the first time, whether or not you want it to. and then contingency ends.</p>
			<p class="indent">The contingent spell takes effect only on you, even if it can normally target others. You can use only one contingency spell at a time. If you cast this spell again, the effect of another contingency spell on you ends. Also, contingency ends on you if its material component is ever not on your person.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">6</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Evocation</set>
			<set name="time">10 minutes</set>
			<set name="duration">10 days</set>
			<set name="range">Self</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a statuette of yourself carved from ivory and decorated with gems worth at least 1,500 gp</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Mass Suggestion" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_MASS_SUGGESTION">
		<supports>Bard, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard, Spell Saving Throw</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You suggest a course of activity (limited to a sentence or two) and magically influence up to twelve creatures of your choice that you can see within range and that can hear and understand you. Creatures that can’t be charmed are immune to this effect. The suggestion must be worded in such a manner as to make the course of action sound reasonable. Asking the creature to stab itself, throw itself onto a spear, immolate itself, or do some other obviously harmful act automatically negates the effect of the spell.</p>
			<p class="indent">Each target must make a Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, it pursues the course of action you described to the best of its ability. The suggested course of action can continue for the entire duration. If the suggested activity can be completed in a shorter time, the spell ends when the subject finishes what it was asked to do.</p>
			<p class="indent">You can also specify conditions that will trigger a special activity during the duration. For example, you might suggest that a group of soldiers give all their money to the first beggar they meet. If the condition isn’t met before the spell ends, the activity isn’t performed.</p>
			<p class="indent">If you or any of your companions damage a creature affected by this spell, the spell ends for that creature.</p>
			<p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a 7th-level spell slot, the duration is 10 days. When you use an 8th-level spell slot, the duration is 30 days. When you use a 9th-level spell slot, the duration is a year and a day.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">6</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Enchantment</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">24 hours</set>
			<set name="range">60 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">false</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a snake’s tongue and either a bit of honeycomb or a drop of sweet oil</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Programmed Illusion" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_PROGRAMMED_ILLUSION">
		<supports>Bard, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You create an illusion of an object, a creature, or some other visible phenomenon within range that activates when a specific condition occurs. The illusion is imperceptible until then. It must be no larger than a 30-foot cube, and you decide when you cast the spell how the illusion behaves and what sounds it makes. This scripted performance can last up to 5 minutes.</p>
			<p class="indent">When the condition you specify occurs, the illusion springs into existence and performs in the manner you described. Once the illusion finishes performing, it disappears and remains dormant for 10 minutes. After this time, the illusion can be activated again.</p>
			<p class="indent">The triggering condition can be as general or as detailed as you like, though it must be based on visual or audible conditions that occur within 30 feet of the area. For example, you could create an illusion of yourself to appear and warn off others who attempt to open a trapped door, or you could set the illusion to trigger only when a creature says the correct word or phrase.</p>
			<p class="indent">Physical interaction with the image reveals it to be an illusion, because things can pass through it. A creature that uses its action to examine the image can determine that it is an illusion with a successful Intelligence (Investigation) check against your spell save DC. If a creature discerns the illusion for what it is, the creature can see through the image, and any noise it makes sounds hollow to the creature.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">6</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Illusion</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Until dispelled</set>
			<set name="range">120 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a bit of fleece and jade dust worth at least 25 gp</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="True Seeing" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_TRUE_SEEING">
		<supports>Bard, Cleric, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>This spell gives the willing creature you touch the ability to see things as they actually are. For the duration, the creature has truesight,  notices secret doors hidden by magic, and can see into the Ethereal Plane, all out to a range of 120 feet.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">6</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Divination</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">1 hour</set>
			<set name="range">Touch</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">an ointment for the eyes that costs 25 gp, is made from mushroom powder, saffron, and fat, and is consumed by the spell</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<!-- 7TH LEVEL -->
	<element name="Etherealness" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_ETHEREALNESS">
		<supports>Bard, Cleric, Sorcerer, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You step into the border regions of the Ethereal Plane, in the area where it overlaps with your current plane. You remain in the Border Ethereal for the duration or until you use your action to dismiss the spell. During this time, you can move in any direction. If you move up or down, every foot of movement costs an extra foot. You can see and hear the plan you originated from, but everything there looks gray, and you can’t see anything more than 60 feet away.</p>
			<p class="indent">While on the Ethereal Plane, you can only affect and be affected by other creatures on that plane. Creatures that aren’t on the Ethereal Plane can’t perceive you and can’t interact with you, unless a special ability or magic has given them the ability to do so.</p>
			<p class="indent">You ignore all objects and effects that aren’t on the Ethereal Plane, allowing you to move through objects you perceive on the plan you originated from.</p>
			<p class="indent">When the spell ends, you immediately return to the plane you originated from in the spot you currently occupy. If you occupy the same spot as a solid object or creature when this happens, you are immediately shunted to the nearest unoccupied space that you can occupy and take force damage equal to twice the number of feet you are moved.</p>
			<p class="indent">This spell has no effect if you cast it while you are on the Ethereal Plane or a plane that doesn’t border it, such as one of the Outer Planes.</p>
			<p class="indent"><b><i>At Higher Levels.</i></b> When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 8th level or higher, you can target up to three willing creatures (including you) for each slot level above 7th. The creatures must be within 10 feet of you when you cast the spell.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">7</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Transmutation</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Up to 8 hours</set>
			<set name="range">Self</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent" />
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Project Image" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_PROJECT_IMAGE">
		<supports>Bard, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You create an illusory copy of yourself that lasts for the duration. The copy can appear at any location within range that you have seen before, regardless of intervening obstacles. The illusion looks and sounds like you but is intangible. If the illusion takes any damage, it disappears, and the spell ends.</p>
			<p class="indent">You can use your action to move this illusion up to twice your speed, and make it gesture, speak, and behave in whatever way you choose. It mimics your mannerisms perfectly.</p>
			<p class="indent">You can see through its eyes and hear through its ears as if you were in its space. On your turn as a bonus action, you can switch from using its senses to using your own, or back again. While you are using its senses, you are blinded and deafened in regard to your own surroundings.</p>
			<p class="indent">Physical interaction with the image reveals it to be an illusion, because things can pass through it. A creature that uses its action to examine the image can determine that it is an illusion with a successful Intelligence (Investigation) check against your spell save DC. If a creature discerns the illusion for what it is, the creature can see through the image, and any noise it makes sounds hollow to the creature.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">7</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Illusion</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 day</set>
			<set name="range">500 miles</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a small replica of you made from materials worth at least 5 gp</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Sequester" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_SEQUESTER">
		<supports>Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>By means of this spell, a willing creature or an object can be hidden away, safe from detection for the duration. When you cast the spell and touch the target, it becomes invisible and can’t be targeted by divination spells or perceived through scrying sensors created by the divination of spells.</p>
			<p class="indent">If the target is a creature, it falls into a state of suspended animation. Time ceases to flow for it, and it doesn’t grow older.</p>
			<p class="indent">You can set a condition for the spell to end early. The condition can be anything you choose, but it must occur or be visible within 1 mile of the target. Examples include after 1,000 years or when the tarrasque awakes. This spells also ends if the target takes any damage.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">7</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Transmutation</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Until dispelled</set>
			<set name="range">Touch</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a powder composed of diamond, emerald, ruby, and sapphire dust worth at least 5,000 gp, which the spell consumes</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<!-- 8TH LEVEL -->
	<element name="Clone" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_CLONE">
		<supports>Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>This spell grows an inert duplicate of a living creature as a safeguard against death. This clone forms inside the vessel used in the spell’s casting and grows to full size and maturity after 120 days; you can also choose to have the clone be a younger version of the same creature. It remains inert and endures indefinitely, as long as its vessel remains undisturbed.</p>
			<p class="indent">At any time after the clone matures, if the original creature dies, its soul transfers to the clone, provided that the soul is free and willing to return. The clone is physically identical to the original and has the same personality, memories, and abilities, but none of the original's equipment. The original creature's physical remains, if they still exist, become inert and can't thereafter be restored to life, since the creature's soul is elsewhere.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">8</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Necromancy</set>
			<set name="time">1 hour</set>
			<set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
			<set name="range">Touch</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a diamond worth at least 1,000 gp and at least 1 cubic inch of flesh of the creature that is to be cloned, which the spell consumes, and a vessel worth at least 2,000 gp that has a sealable lid and is large enough to hold the creature being cloned, such as a huge urn, coffin, mud-filled cyst in the ground, or crystal container filled with salt water</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Feeblemind" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_FEEBLEMIND">
		<supports>Bard, Druid, Warlock, Wizard, Spell Saving Throw</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You blast the mind of a creature that you can see within range, attempting to shatter its intellect and personality. The target takes 4d6 psychic damage and must make an Intelligence saving throw.</p>
			<p class="indent">On a failed save, the creature’s Intelligence and Charisma scores become 1. The creature can’t cast spells, activate magic items, understand language, or communicate in any intelligible way. The creature can, however, identify its friends, follow them, and even protect them.</p>
			<p class="indent">At the end of every 30 days, the creature can repeat its saving throw against this spell. If it succeeds on its saving throw, the spell ends.</p>
			<p class="indent">The spell can also be ended by greater restoration, heal or wish.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords">psychic</set>
			<set name="level">8</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Enchantment</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Instantaneous</set>
			<set name="range">150 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a handful of clay, crystal, glass, or mineral spheres</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Mind Blank" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_MIND_BLANK">
		<supports>Bard, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>Until the spell ends, one willing creature you touch is immune to psychic damage, any effect that would sense its emotions or read its thoughts, divination spells, and the charmed condition. The spell even foils wish spells and spells or effects of similar power used to affect the target’s mind or to gain information about the target.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">8</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Abjuration</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">24 hours</set>
			<set name="range">Touch</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">false</set>
			<set name="materialComponent" />
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	
	<!-- 9TH LEVEL -->
	<element name="Imprisonment" type="Spell" source="Player’s Handbook" id="ID_PHB_SPELL_IMPRISONMENT">
		<supports>Warlock, Wizard, Spell Saving Throw</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You create a magical restraint to hold a creature that you can see within range. The target must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or be bound by the spell; if it succeeds, it is immune to this spell if you cast it again. While affected by this spell, the creature doesn't need to breathe, eat, or drink, and it doesn't age. Divination spells can't locate or perceive the target.</p>
			<p class="indent">When you cast the spell, you choose one of the following forms of imprisonment.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><i>Burial. </i></strong>The target is entombed far beneath the earth in a sphere of magical force that is just large enough to contain the target. Nothing can pass through the sphere, nor can any creature teleport or use planar travel to get into or out of it.</p>
			<p class="indent">The special component for this version of the spell is a small mithral orb.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><i>Chaining. </i></strong>Heavy chains, firmly rooted in the ground, hold the target in place. The target is restrained until the spell ends, and it can't move or be moved by any means until then.</p>
			<p class="indent">The special component for this version of the spell is a fine chain of precious metal.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><i>Hedged Prison. </i></strong>The spell transports the target into a tiny demiplane that is warded against teleportation and planar travel. The demiplane can be a labyrinth, a cage, a tower, or any similar confined structure or area of your choice.</p>
			<p class="indent">The special component for this version of the spell is a miniature representation of the prison made from jade.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><i>Minimus Containment. </i></strong>The target shrinks to a height of 1 inch and is imprisoned inside a gemstone or similar object. Light can pass through the gemstone normally (allowing the target to see out and other creatures to see in), but nothing else can pass through, even by means of teleportation or planar travel. The gemstone can't be cut or broken while the spell remains in effect.</p>
			<p class="indent">The special component for this version of the spell is a large, transparent gemstone, such as a corundum, diamond, or ruby.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><i>Slumber. </i></strong>The target falls asleep and can't be awoken. The special component for this version of the spell consists of rare soporific herbs.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><i>Ending the Spell. </i></strong>During the casting of the spell, in any of its versions, you can specify a condition that will cause the spell to end and release the target. The condition can be as specific or as elaborate as you choose, but the GM must agree that the condition is reasonable and has a likelihood of coming to pass. The conditions can be based on a creature's name, identity, or deity but otherwise must be based on observable actions or qualities and not based on intangibles such as level, class, or hit points.</p>
			<p class="indent">A dispel magic spell can end the spell only if it is cast as a 9th-level spell, targeting either the prison or the special component used to create it.</p>
			<p class="indent">You can use a particular special component to create only one prison at a time. If you cast the spell again using the same component, the target of the first casting is immediately freed from its binding.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">9</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Abjuration</set>
			<set name="time">1 minute</set>
			<set name="duration">Until dispelled</set>
			<set name="range">30 feet</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a vellum depiction or a carved statuette in the likeness of the target, and a special component that varies according to the version of the spell you choose, worth at least 500 gp per Hit Die of the target</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Foresight" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_FORESIGHT">
		<supports>Bard, Druid, Warlock, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You touch a willing creature and bestow a limited ability to see into the immediate future. For the duration, the target can’t be surprised and has advantage on attack rolls, ability checks, and saving throws. Additionally, other creatures have disadvantage on attack rolls against the target for the duration.</p>
			<p class="indent">This spell immediately ends if you cast it again before its duration ends.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">9</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Divination</set>
			<set name="time">1 minute</set>
			<set name="duration">8 hours</set>
			<set name="range">Touch</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a hummingbird feather</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">false</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
	<element name="Shapechange" type="Spell" source="Orana's Expanded Spellbook" id="ID_PP_OES_SPELL_SHAPECHANGE">
		<supports>Druid, Wizard</supports>
		<description>
			<p>You assume the form of a different creature for the duration. The new form can be any creature with a challenge rating equal to your level or lower. The creature can’t be a construct or an undead, and you must have seen the sort of creature at least once. You transform into an average example of that creature, one without any class levels or the Spellcasting trait.</p>
			<p class="indent">Your game statistics are replaced by the statistics of the chosen creature, though you retain your alignment and Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma scores You also retain all of your skill and saving throw proficiencies, in addition to gaining those of the creature, If the creature has the same proficiency as you, and the bonus listed in its statistics is higher than yours, use the creature’s bonus in place of yours. You can’t use any legendary actions or lair actions of the new form.</p>
			<p class="indent">You assume the hit points and Hit Dice of the new form. When you revert to your normal, you return to the number of hit points you had before you transformed. If you revert as a result of dropping to 0 hit points, any excess damage carries over to your normal form. As long as the excess damage doesn’t reduce your normal form to 0 hit points, you aren’t knocked unconscious.</p>
			<p class="indent">You retain the benefit of any features from your class, race, or other source and can use them, provided that your new form is physically capable of doing so. You can’t use any special senses you have (for example, darkvision) unless your new form also has that sense. You can only speak if the creature can normally speak.</p>
			<p class="indent">When you transform, you choose whether your equipment falls to the ground, merges into the new form, or is worn by it. Worn equipment functions as normal. The DM determines whether it is practical for the new form to wear a piece of equipment, based on the creature’s shape and size. Your equipment doesn’t change shape or size to match the new form, and any equipment that the new form can’t wear must either fall to the ground or merge into your new form. Equipment that merges has no effect in that state.</p>
			<p class="indent">During this spell’s duration, you can use your action to assume a different form following the same restrictions and rules for the original form, with one exception: if your new form has more hit pints than your current one, your hit points remain at their current value.</p>
		</description>
		<setters>
			<set name="keywords"></set>
			<set name="level">9</set>
			<set name="school" addition="Spycraft">Transmutation</set>
			<set name="time">1 action</set>
			<set name="duration">Concentration, up to 1 hour</set>
			<set name="range">Self</set>
			<set name="hasVerbalComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasSomaticComponent">true</set>
			<set name="hasMaterialComponent">true</set>
			<set name="materialComponent">a jade circlet worth at least 1,500 gp, which you must place on your head before you cast the spell</set>
			<set name="isConcentration">true</set>
			<set name="isRitual">false</set>
		</setters>
	</element>
</elements>